Finding Aid for Michigan Synodical Association Records 1873-1973
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Synodical Association Records 1873-1973, 1942-1968
Michigan Synodical Association.
2 linear feet
852107 Ba 2
Women's organization of the Michigan Synod of the Presbyterian Church of Michigan formed in 1919 through merger of the Michigan Woman's Foreign Missionary Society and the Michigan Woman's Foreign Missionary Society. papers include administrative files, annual reports, and minutes of committees and annual meetings
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Records were donated by Mrs. Maurine V. Jones (Donor No. 4793 ), April 13, 1973.
The collection is open for research.
The Michigan Synodical Society (now Association) was formed from several women's societies within the Presbyterian Church of Michigan. Women had from the beginning of the church in Michigan played an important role. Though they had early organized themselves into presbyterials, not until 1873 did they form a synodical-level mission society to be called the Michigan Woman's Foreign Missionary Society. Six years later, in 1879, a second society, the Michigan Woman's Board of Home Missions, was established. Though these two synodical organizations, the women of the local presbyterials were now able to participate in a fuller sense in the goals of the church, especially as they related to the home and foreign mission fields.
By 1898 the Michigan Woman's Foreign Missionary Society supported fourteen missionaries, corresponded with different presbyteries advising them about their missions program, and arranged visits of missionaries home on furlough. Although the Women's Board of Home Missions supported missionaries all over the United States, an important part of its work was with the Detroit Mission of the Presbytery of Detroit. Here the board pioneered work among Italian and Hungarian immigrants to the city, appointing women to minister to the women and children of these communities. In 1885, the Women's Board of Home Missions, through the Detroit Mission, began a program of support to freedmen now living in Michigan. In 1919 the two synodical societies (Foreign Missions and Home Missions) merged to form the Michigan Synodical Society. The first meeting of the two, now joined, organizations was held in Monroe, Michigan in 1920.
In the early 1930s the function of presbyterials changed as presbyterial boundaries were redrawn. As a result, the character of the Michigan Synodical Society also changed with more emphasis given to developing leadership abilities among the church women. Despite these changes, missions remained a primary focus of the society. In 1961, the designation "presbyterial" was dropped, and the local presbyterial-level groups were known simply as the United Presbyterian Women. In 1968, the name of the organization was changed to Michigan Synodical Association, and in 1969, it became part of the Synodical of the Covenant, covering the area of Michigan, Ohio, and Kentucky.
The records have been divided into three series and several sub-series:
Historical Material
Administration
Presbyterials
Minutes, newsletters, etc.
Annual Meeting Booklets and Year Books
Within each series the arrangement is primarily chronologically.
The records of the Michigan Synodical Society document its historical development, the administration of its business, its annual meetings, and its interests in missions, both foreign and home missions, from 1873 to 1973. These records document the beginnings of both the foreign (1873) and home (1879) missionary societies which eventually became the Michigan Synodical Society (1919). The bulk of the collection, however, covers the later period, 1942-1968.
Subjects:
Michigan Synodical Association.; Women--Religious life--Michigan.; United Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A.--Michigan.; Women in the Presbyterian Church--Michigan.
- Historical Materials 1873-1962
  The Historical Materials series is comprised of materials relating to all four organizations encompassed by the Michigan Synodical Society, and covers the years 1873-1962. Each committee has been assigned a folder. The fifth folder in this series contains constitutions and bylaws of both mission committees, the Michigan Synodical Society, and almost every presbyterial, 1882-1969. Of particular interest is a list of the names and places of origin in Michigan of the Presbyterian missionaries sent all over the world, a booklet printed by the Detroit Mission arm of the Woman's Board of Home Missions (c.1919), a booklet printed for the Silver Jubilee of the Foreign Missionary Society (1898), and an historical summary of the Board of Home Missions as delivered at its Golden Jubilee in 1929. It should be noted that although there is reference in these folders to minutes of both committees, the minutes recorded prior to 1942 are not included. In the one hundred years covering the history of the Michigan Synodical Society, a handful of women stand out in leadership and dedicated service. Particular mention should be made of Mrs. Agnes Moffit Mitchell [1856-1933] who served as president of Home Missions, 1908-1919, and then went on to lead the new Synodical Society, 1919-1931.
  - Michigan Woman's Foreign Missionary Society, 1873-1955 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Woman's Board of Home Missions, 1879-1929 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Synodical Society, 1873-1962
    - General 1919-1969 (Box 1)
    - Election of Synodical Officers 1873-1955 (Box 1)
    - Memorials of Synodical Officers 1873-1955 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Presbyterials 1932-1955 (Box 1)
  - Constitutions and By-Laws 1882-1969 (Box 1)
- Administration 1933-1971
  The second series concerns the Administration of the Michigan Synodical Society, 1933-1971. This series consists of two major categories of materials: the minutes of the society, 1942-1968, and files relating to its stewardship called "Goals and Giving" and covering the years, 1955-1968. The minutes have been organized chronologically by year, interweaving the minutes of the annual meetings (June) and the mid-Winter executive meetings (January), with any additional executive meetings that might have occurred.
  The remainder of this series consists of files reflecting the responsibilities and interests of the association. The synodical put out its own newsletter, called the Michigan Synodical Signpos t (later becoming the Michigan Messenger). Only a few copies of very few years are part of this collection: 1948-1950, 1959. One folder marks the relationship between Felicia Sunderlal from India and the women of the association. It begins with preparation for her arrival in 1954 and closes with her mother's communication of her death in 1962. There are two folders containing summary information: "Annual Meeting Booklets (with Year Book information), 1941-1959," and "Year Books, 1958/1959-1970/1971." Prior to 1959 the Annual Meeting Booklets contained information later found in the Society's year books. However, they also included the order of service which opened the annual meeting, as well as the agenda for the meeting.
  - Minutes of Annual and Mid Winter Executive Meetings 1942-1968, 27 folders (Box 1)
  - Goals and Giving 1955-1968, 14 folders (Box 1)
  - Alma College, 1957-1964 (Box 2)
  - Annual Meeting Booklets (with year book information) 1941-1959 (Box 2)
  - Annual Reports to Synod 1942-1968 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence between Synodical and Presbyterial Presidents 1964-1968 (Box 2)
  - Membership 1956-1965 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Synodical Signpost (later Michigan Synodical Messenger), 1948-1950, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Sunderlal, Felicia, 1954-1962 (Box 2)
  - Training opportunities 1933-1969 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
  - Year Books 1958/1959-1970/1971 (Box 2)
- Presbyterials 1925-1973
  The Presbyterials series, includes a subseries of executive and annual meeting minutes, with occasional newsletters of the different presbyterials, arranged alphabetically. It also includes a second subseries of annual meeting booklets and year books, also arranged alphabetically.
  - Minutes, newsletters, etc.
    - Detroit
      - General 1954-1970 (Box 2)
      - Retreats circa 1915-1925?, 1956-1962 (Box 2)
    - Grand River, 1964-1970 (Box 2)
    - Mackinac, 1955-1970 (Box 2)
    - Southern Michigan, 1964-1969 (Box 2)
  - Annual Meeting Booklets and Year Books
    - Detroit, 1925, 1930, 1931-1961, 1962-1973 (Box 2)
    - Lansing, 1939-1961 (Box 2)
    - Grand River (formed when the Grand Rapids and Lansing Presbyteries were joined in 1961), 1962-1968 (Box 2)
    - Flint, 1931, 1939-April 1961 (Box 2)
    - Saginaw, 1931, 1939-April 1961 (Box 2)
    - Lake Huron (formed when the Flint and Saginaw Presbyteries were joined in 1961), Fall 1961-1968 (Box 2)
    - Mackinac (formed when the Lake Superior and Petoskey Presbyteries were joined in 1961) 1962-1969 (Box 2)
    - Petoskey, 1939-1961 (Box 2)
    - Grand Rapids, 1937-1945 (Box 2)
    - Southern Michigan (formed when Western Michigan Presbytery was split to form the Grand River and the Southern Michigan Presbyteries in 1961), 1962-1968
    - Western Michigan (formed when the Grand Rapids and Kalamazoo Presbyteries were joined in 1946), 1946-1961 (Box 2)